YOAOUIM CINTRON

Engineering Leader, Software Engineer

SUMMARY

Passionate Software Engineering Leader with 10+ years of experience in developing web applications and backend systems. Able to lead and grow Engineering teams. Skilled at writing clear, concise code that is easy to maintain and troubleshoot. Experienced in working with both small and large teams across multiple projects and companies.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Platform Lead, Data Architect Lead, Manager - Consultant Allied World

2022-2023

Remote

- Build platform to centralize and analyze Data across all product teams
- Delivered a dynamic Data Platform with on-demand reports capability
- · Revolutionized Data Delivery by engineering a Platform that reduced time from Months to Days
- · Build Data Platform Infrastructure using Terraform, CDK, and Chalice
- Build Infrastructure via Terraform and AWS for Insurance Portal
- Led team, on both infrastructure and application development, on delivering Portal

Head of Devops, Senior Engineering Manager

2019-2022

Attune Insurance

Remote

- Transition all infrastructure from legacy cloud to AWS, reducing annual costs by \$1.2 million
- Developed a platform providing each employee with a personal, fully-integrated environment
- Manage engineers across teams, coduct performance reviews and mentoring
- Oversee managers and engineering teams, fostering a productive and collaborative culture
- Cross-functional leader: integrate and manage projects across the entire company
- Implemented entire logging, monitoring, and alerting stack for all services and systems
- Terraform (Infrastructure-as-Code) all infrastructure, including IAM users and permissions
- Responsible for overseeing Security Initiatives and managing Technical Compliance

Senior Frontend & Backend Engineer, DevOps Engineer, Manager Intent Media

New York/Remote

2015-2018

- · Led and mentored junior engineers as the DevOps Lead for the Data Engineering Team
- · Delivery Lead for the Backend Team, ensuring project goals and timelines were met effectively
- Overhauled the in-house frontend framework for better delivery and performance of frontend
- Developed a service for delivering model predictions using trained models
- · Managed the migration of legacy systems to AWS, utilizing ECS, Lambda, and S3
- · Implemented a serverless, high-traffic API on AWS
- Automated testing and deployment processes (CI/CD) for squad products

Frontend Engineer

2015-2015 New York

Hackerati

• Led as a consultant on new initiatives and tackled complex software challenges.

- Specialized in scalable frontend solutions and team expansion to meet critical deadlines
- Steered internal projects from inception to public product conceptualization
- Developed and deployed a successful e-commerce application using Angular
- Actively engaged as a consultant on various client projects
- Directed in-house initiatives and projects, demonstrating leadership and strategic planning

Software Engineer Optivon

2013-2014

Puerto Rico

• Key contributor in the product development team for a law enforcement software suite

- · Led the development of web application, encompassing backend, frontend, and infrastructure
- Served as the technical lead, responsible for technology stack, DevOps, and solution strategies
- Designed and developed an integrated system comprising an Android app, Web app, and API
- Versatile role encompassing technical development, design, sales, and interdisciplinary tasks



ACHIEVEMENTS

Grew Engineering Team by Over 150%, focusing on delivery

Hired, mentored, and developed over a dozen engineers across different teams

Strategic AWS Transition Yielded \$1.2 Million in Annual Cost Savings

Migrated from legacy cloud to AWS, modernizing infrastructure

Enhanced Developer Efficiency by 70% with Custom In-House Tool

Built platform where developers had their own version of production

Transformed Data Delivery: Cut Time from 6 Months to 3 Days

Engineering platform that delivered ETL data in days rather than months

STRENGTHS

Engineering Leadership

Building Teams

Project Delivery

Platform Engineering

Frontend Engineering

Cloud Operations

Developer Operations

SKILLS

Languages & Frameworks

Typescript • Python • Javascript • Java Terraform • PostgreSQL• Tailwind • React Ionic • CDK • FastAPI • Redshift • Bash Serverless • NodeJS • Chalice

Tools

AWS • Redshift • Lambda • S3 • Fargate Windmill • Airflow • Docker • GH Actions GPT • CI/CD • Airbyte

EDUCATION

B.Sc. Computer Engineering University of Puerto Rico at Mayagüez

2007-2014

Puerto Rico

PROJECTS

zemi

github.com/yoaquim/zemi

OSS Data-driven API Framework

- Data-driven and reverse-routing library for ExpressJs
- Built from scratch with Typescript, tests, maintainability, CI/CD pipelines, and documentation
- Declarative, data-driven configuration and recursive library
- 100% code coverage, Grade A Codeclimate Maintainability, and Comprehensive documentation

Sandboxes Attune Insurance

On-Demand, Personal Development Environments

- Enabled employees to create controlled replicas of our production environment via a UI
- Each Sandbox supported individualized service versions within our stack
- Revolutionized testing by facilitating comprehensive tests in near-production conditions
- · Rapid testing tool: Product Owners could test changes ASAP, and with high confidence
- Graphical Interface made using easy, especially for non-tech stakeholders
- · Ability to deploy any service's (e.g. api, frontend) Git branch to a given Sandbox
- Each Sandbox user had their own link, which mapped to their own cloud space

Harvester Allied World

Centralized Data Platform

- Centralized Data Platform enabling Product Teams to specify data processing requirements
- Facilitated data uploads through both API and GUI, with automatic availability in Redshift
- Utilized Airflow and Airbyte for data orchestration and processing from diverse sources
- Implemented comprehensive data governance across the organization
- · Leveraged Windmill for rapid prototyping and delivery of backend code and data pipelines
- · Achieved full operational status within two weeks.

SWRPG Manager

swrpgmanager.yoaquim.com

Game Management Web App

- · Daily usage, growing userbase
- Full web app using React, Tailwind, Supabase, AWS, Github Actions, and MixPanel